Finding aid to the Myra M. Sampson Papers CA.MS.00311
Smith College Archives
Myra M. Sampson Papers
1888-1984
Smith College Archives
Sampson, Myra M., 1887-1984
CA.MS.00311
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
Professor of Zoology. Contains correspondence, clippings, notes, reports, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Myra Sampson was born on January 31, 1887 in Fall River, Massachusetts. Sampson received her Ph.B. from Brown University, and both her M.D. and Ph.D. from the University of Michigan. A member of the Smith College faculty from 1909 to 1955, Sampson was a professor of Zoology and became Chairman of the Committee on Graduate Study. With an interest in bacteriology and physiology, Sampson was an expert on nutrition and Vitamin A, and directed a research project determining the effect on the thyroid gland of an excess or deficiency of calcium. Not only was Sampson involved with the college, she served on the Northampton Board of Health from 1947-1950, and conducted fatigue tests for the U.S. Navy during World War II. Sampson also researched overseas, and conducted experiments at the Dunn Nutritional Laboratory in Cambridge, England and at the Lister Foundation in London. Sampson passed away February 29, 1984 in Northampton, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains correspondence, clippings, obituaries, field notes, and various reports regarding Smith College faculty and alumnae. Also included in the collection are materials relating to her stay at Cold Spring Harbor and her tenure working for the Red Cross. In addition, there are also photographs of Sampson herself, and of various renowned scientists.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Myra M. Sampson papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Zoology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Massachusetts -- Northampton.; Biological laboratory -- Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y.; black-and-white photographs; correspondence; cartes-de-visite (card photographs); exhibit scripts; laboratory notes; Satina, Sophia, 1879 - 1975; Smith College -- Faculty.; Smith College -- Alumni and alumnae -- History -- Sources.; Marine Biological Laboratory (Woods Hole, Mass.); Sampson, Myra M., 1887-1984
- Biographical information, 1888-1984 (Box 1003, Folder 1)
- Biographical information, 1941-1984 (Box 1003, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: general, 1905-1982 (Box 1003, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Sophie Satina, 1917-1976 (Box 1003, Folder 4)
- Clippings, 1939-1984 (Box 1003, Folder 5)
- Cold Spring Harbor song books, 1910-1921 (Box 1003, Folder 6)
- Faculty: the study of, 1957-1970 (Box 1003, Folder 7)
- Field notes: Fort Davis, Texas, 1914 (Box 1003, Folder 8)
- Lab studies in physiology, 1928 (Box 1003, Folder 9)
- Red Cross activities/housing information, 1956-1959 (Box 1003, Folder 10)
- Report on the status of women faculty, 1956-1972 (Box 1003, Folder 11)
- Smith alumnae degrees and graduate study, 1924-1925; undated (Box 1003, Folder 12)
- Smith alumnae with degrees in science, 1966; undated (Box 1003, Folder 13)
- Smith alumnae with M.D. degrees, 1954-1968 (Box 1003, Folder 14)
- Smith alumnae with Ph.D. degrees, 1961-1968 (Box 1003, Folder 15)
- Smith College history, 1928-1974 (Box 1003, Folder 16)
- Publications and clippings, 1922-1962 (Box 1003.1, Folder 17)
- Photographs and signatures of scientists, 1906-1942 (Box 1003.1, Folder 18)
- Darwin Exhibition, undated (Box 1003.1, Folder 19)